Let me show you a video.
>> Andy Burnham, the Labour and Cooperative
Party, 24,927.
>> This is the moment it was announced that
British Labour Party politician Andy
Burnham had managed to secure [music] a
seat.
It was the first domino in a series of
events which would lead to him being
elevated from Mayor of Greater
Manchester to the next Prime Minister of
the United Kingdom. But, I don't want to
talk to you about Andy Burnham. I want
to talk to you about these guys. Stood
to Burnham's left, and yes, dressed as a
fox, is Robert Pownall. Pownall is the
founder of an organization called
Protect the Wild, a campaign group which
works to oppose countryside blood sports
and other forms of wildlife culling in
the UK. Pownall and his organization are
particularly opposed to fox hunting,
hence the outfit. And this wasn't his
first time running for office, either.
Two months previously, Robert had run to
become a member of Scottish Parliament
dressed as a giant gannet. Pownall did
atrociously in both those elections. In
Scotland, he got just 41 votes. And in
Wakefield, he managed just 18. That's in
comparison to Andy Burnham's
>> 24,927.
>> But, that's not the point. For Pownall,
participating in elections is not about
winning power, not directly anyway. It's
about using the media buzz which
surrounds these contests to push the
barbarism of aristocratic blood sports
up the political agenda. This clip of
him stood next to the next Prime
Minister was played again and again and
again on the news in the wake of the
Wakefield by-election. And yeah, the
fact that there was a dude dressed as a
fox stood there did probably get people
to think about fox hunting more than
they otherwise might have. Heck, I'm
talking to you about it now. Britain has
a small army of activists and campaign
groups which try to use elections in
this way. The Wakefield by-election also
had a candidate for the Rejoin EU Bring
in PR Party. Some years ago, there was a
party called the Cannabis is Safer Than
Alcohol Party. There's also a guy called
Bobby Smith who regularly runs for
office dressed as Elmo, which you might
think is him being a joke candidate, but
he actually runs as Elmo as part of a
protest about the fact that he's not
allowed to see his [music] kids anymore.
Maybe not the best way to make that
case. At risk of underlining the point
too much, none of these people have
anything in the way of actual electoral
prospects. The impact of their running
is limited entirely to getting their
slogan and name [music] printed on the
ballot paper, and if they're lucky,
maybe said out loud on TV once or twice.
Maybe they'll be so lucky that someone
will decide to make a YouTube video
about novelty candidates in which their
reasons for running get discussed. But
then
there's this guy. This is Count Binface.
Like the fox and Elmo, Count Binface has
also run for office before.
A lot. He ran against Boris Johnson in
Uxbridge in the 2019 general election.
He ran against Sadiq Khan in the 2021
and 2024 London mayoral elections. He
ran again in Uxbridge after Boris
Johnson resigned in 2023. And he ran
against Rishi Sunak in the 2024 general
election while Sunak was still Prime
Minister and leader of the Conservative
Party. Count Binface's careful selection
of races to stand in means that he's
managed to get on TV perhaps more than
Robert Peston or any of those other
single-issue candidates ever have. Here
he is being interviewed by Sky News.
Here he is being interviewed by the
Mirror. Here he is absolutely
demolishing GB News.
>> Tell us about your policies here in
Wakefield if you were to be successful.
>> Absolutely. Firstly, all news operations
should obey Ofcom rules. Secondly, all
news operations should obey Ofcom rules,
and I could go on.
>> Quick sidebar for international viewers,
Ofcom is the UK's media regulator, which
is meant [music] to uphold a rule which
means that broadcast TV should be
impartial, and is kind of meant to make
a UK version of Fox News impossible. And
GB News is effectively just a UK version
of Fox News. So, what policies does
Count Binface use this platform to
promote?
>> Uh
Price capping croissants. Renaming
London Bridge after Phoebe Waller. And
here's a new one, making Thames Water
bosses take a dip in the Thames to see
how they like it.
>> Sorry, another sidebar for international
viewers, Thames Water is a water company
in the UK which keeps leaking human [__]
into rivers. So, yeah, but risk of being
the boring guy who explains the joke,
those aren't real policies.
They're jokes.
>> Haha.
>> If single-issue candidates have become a
marginal feature of British politics in
recent years, novelty candidate, sorry,
decades-long [screaming and cheering]
and much-loved tradition. US presidents
get to celebrate their election wins at
highly choreographed rallies, in
stadiums and convention centers.
Candidates for British Prime Minister
have to learn the results while stood
next to an old geezer in an oversized
cowboy hat. Through a strange twist of
history, however, novelty candidates are
about to get serious. When Nigel Farage,
the leader of the far-right Reform
Party, faces a by-election in the coming
week or weeks, depending on when this
goes out, there is set to be only one
meaningful contender standing in his
way,
Count Binface.
For reasons we'll come to, none of the
other major parties have opted to run
against Farage, who is currently under
investigation for allegedly failing to
declare political donations, which
leaves Binface as the only opponent with
any kind of name recognition. In today's
video, I want to take a deep dive into
how novelty candidates became such a big
feature in British politics, and of
course, whether the bin can win.
>> MY NAME IS HOWLING Lord Hope.
I'm the leader of the official Monster
Raving Loony Party.
>> So, yeah. You probably know already the
Count Binface isn't the UK's only
novelty political candidate. In fact,
[music] Count Binface isn't even the
first novelty candidate which Count
Binface has run [music] as.
>> That's right.
On your knees, earthlings.
>> This is Lord Buckethead, or one of them.
In 2017, a TV writer and comedian called
John Harvey decided to run as a
candidate in the general election of
that year, and that he would do so
dressed as a character called Lord
Buckethead. Buckethead was taken from a
1984 Star Wars parody film [music]
called Hyperspace, although which was
retitled Gremlins in the UK market
because apparently Brits prefer worse
[music] titles for things.
>> What kind of outfit you call that?
>> To make matters slightly more
complicated, whilst Lord Buckethead was
John Harvey's first novelty political
persona, Harvey wasn't the first person
to run for office as Lord Buckethead.
That honor fell to a man called Mike
Lee. See, Gremlins was distributed in
the UK by a company called Vipco, which
focused mainly on low-budget horror
flicks and cash-grab B movies. This was
the 1980s when selling stuff like this
required getting physical shops to stock
physical VHS tapes, and for people to
actually go out and request and buy them
rather than just stumble upon them in
the sloppier depths of Amazon Prime,
where everything is just called
something like Shark Exorcist.
>> We're not talking about a normal shark
here.
>> Vipco's boss, Mike Lee, decided that the
best way to promote a film about a Darth
Vader-style character trying to seize
power would be to run for office against
then Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher
during the 1987 general election. Lee
would then repeat the stunt again
against John Major in 1992, [music]
receiving 107 votes to John Major's
>> 48,000
662.
>> When John Harvey decided to place the
bucket on his head in 2017, then, he was
in some respects donning a piece of
British political history. And yet, he
was also picking up the mantle of a
commercial film character, even if not a
particularly commercially or
artistically successful one.
>> Is this the best your planet has to
offer?
>> Harvey's run as Lord Buckethead gained a
lot of traction. He was in the papers,
[music] he was on TV. By the time the
election came around, he'd been flown
over to the US to appear on Last Week
Tonight with [music] John Oliver.
>> I am now able to present to you here
tonight your new Brexit negotiator.
PLEASE WELCOME LORD [cheering]
BUCKETHEAD. [screaming]
>> [music]
>> THE result was that it came to the
attention of Todd Durham, the director
of Hyperspace/Gremliod,
whichever you prefer. Durham had, by
this point, gone on to such heights of
creating the concept for the Hotel
[music] Transylvania series of films.
Although, and I'm no expert in how
Hollywood works, it appears he's only
credited with the initial idea and
story, and that the films themselves,
which were actually developed and
directed by someone else.
>> Real Count Dracula, like, "I'm Dracula,
blah, blah, blah."
>> I've never said that in my life. Blah,
blah, blah. I don't know where that
comes from.
>> Either way, Durham apparently got a bit
cagey about Lord Buckethead's revived
political career. Durham, whose
filmography consists of a knock-off Star
Wars film and a knock-off kids' Dracula
film is apparently really hot on
copyright. He therefore ended up forcing
Harvey to hand over the login to the
Lord Buckethead Twitter account, after
which Harvey set about creating his own
completely distinct and [music]
impossible to confuse character, Count
Binface. A further twist in this tale
[music] came in 2019 when that Lord
Buckethead Twitter account started
tweeting once again, suggesting that
Buckethead might run against Nigel
Farage in the 2019 European Parliament
elections uh and it crowdfunded £15,000
in order to do so. At recent elections,
Lord Buckethead has been portrayed by
someone called David Hughes, who had
also worked for Vit C back in the day.
Although for the upcoming by-election in
Clacton, the Lord has chosen to endorse
the count. It's a lot.
>> I, Lord Buckethead, have decided to
endorse the only serious candidate in
the Clacton by-election. I speak, of
course, of my intergalactic counterpart,
Count Binface.
>> But the idea that there should be all of
this conflict over one particular
novelty character is kind of bizarre.
Because Britain has a decades-long
history of people running for office
whilst dressed in silly costumes.
>> [music]
>> This is Jack the Ripper, a not quite
smash hit single by David Sutch, more
commonly known by his stage name
Screaming Lord Sutch. Sutch was a big
mover and shaker in the music scene of
the 1960s. His later album, Lord Sutch
and Heavy Friends, featured Jimmy Page,
John Bonham, and Jeff Beck.
It was also, in a 1998 poll carried out
by the BBC, voted the worst album of all
time. Today, vanishingly few people
would even know that Screaming Lord
Sutch was ever a musician at all. And
that's because his greatest contribution
to British culture came in his being the
founder of the Official Monster Raving
>> Good voters of Rochdale,
I am Dick the Flying Brick and candidate
for the Official Monster Raving Loony
Party in the recent by-election in
Wellingborough.
>> So, in 1963, Sutch decided to run for
Parliament in a by-election in
Stratford-on-Avon.
And he did so as the only candidate for
the National Teenage Party. There were
some genuine political motivations
behind this move. At the time, the
minimum voting age in the UK remained
21, which to Sutch seemed pretty
indefensible, particularly during an era
of such a vibrant and politically
engaged youth [music] culture.
Sutch campaigned then on a platform of
extending the vote to teenagers. And
yet, Sutch also brought the
theatricality of his musical
performances to his campaigning. "Vote
for the ghoul, he's no fool." ran one of
the slogans. "Down with Sutch and up
with idiots." ran another. When the New
York Times paid Stratford a visit to
report on the campaign, they couldn't
help but highlight this strange figure
campaigning in a top hat. If Sutch's
serious political message about youth
disenfranchisement [music]
and his wacky campaigning style seemed
to be intentional, it was the latter
which won out.
Screaming Lord Sutch would stand in 40
elections and by-elections throughout
his life, rarely receiving more than a
few thousand votes. In 1982, he even
opened things up to others who fancied a
go as well. The Official Monster Raving
Loony Party was founded in 1982 in a pub
in Ashburton in Devon. [music]
The town which, fun this isn't relevant
to this video at all, is notable for
being the only British town that I'm
aware of which has as its most famous
landmark a life-size AT-ST. I drive past
this all the time and it's honestly just
really nice to have an opportunity to
talk about it in public. In 1983, the
Looneys ran 11 candidates across the UK
with Screaming Lord Sutch running
against Margaret Thatcher in Finchley.
The movement took off and the Looneys
became a staple of British electoral
culture. Under the leadership of Sutch's
successor, Howling Lord Hope, the party
stood 22 candidates [music] in the 2024
general election including Nick the
Incredible Flying Brick, Lord Sychar
Billy Tractor, and Sir Grumpus El
Shorticus. The party's manifesto
included policies such as reducing
hospital waiting lists by using a
smaller font, making Britain fairer by
introducing a court of human lefts, and
on immigration replacing employees of
the border force with GP receptionists
to reduce the number of people getting
in. In recent years though, things have
exploded. There have been multiple
British YouTubers who have run for
election as a bet in recent years
including Max Fosh and Nico Omilana. Tom
Scott also happens to have run as a
novelty candidate in the past, although
I think before he was a YouTuber, so
just kind of for the fun of the game. In
Clacton, there will be 34 separate
candidates on the ballot paper. Some of
them genuine, some of them single issue
candidates, many of them novelty
characters. The Official Monster Raving
Loony Party is fielding three candidates
in the same constituency, something
which might be a first for British
politics.
>> [music]
>> If you know otherwise, please write in
and let me know. For fans of the
Looneys, Binface, and other novelty
candidates, all of this is wonderful,
right? It is a sign of how open the
British political system is. Yes, in
practice, the parties might have a
stranglehold on things, but anyone still
[music] can run. Before we celebrate
this principle too much, however, it's
probably worth highlighting that this
ease of standing is not as old as we
sometimes assume and kind of came about
by accident.
>> In the name of Oog the Beneficent, the
Merciful, all praise is due to Oog, for
he is Lord of all the worlds.
I want to thank you all for electing me
for MP tonight, and my reign will begin
from today. [__] Broadstairs.
>> So, yeah. If the 34 candidates running
in Clacton hasn't made it clear enough,
it is really easy to run for office in
the UK. Really easy. Particularly for an
MPC. See, in many other countries, even
getting your name on the ballot for a
national election is either really
difficult or really expensive.
>> Today, we are out collecting signatures
at [music] the No Kings March to try to
get her back on the ballot.
>> We have over 10,000
signatures.
>> In the US, these are known as ballot
access requirements. If you live in
Illinois and want to run for a seat in
the US House of Representatives as an
independent candidate, you're likely to
need to gather more than 10,000
nomination signatures. Running for the
House of Representatives in Japan
requires putting up a deposit of at
least 3 million yen, which is around
13,700
pounds or just shy of 18,500 [music]
dollars. It's worth saying that there is
a rationale behind this, which isn't
just about keeping people off the ballot
for nefarious purposes. [music]
A ballot paper which is packed with
dozens of candidates is not going to be
particularly easy to navigate for
voters. Even if one candidate doesn't
try to take advantage of the situation
and just enter a load of mates as fake
candidates with similar names or
something, it's just a lot to ask voters
to choose between 34 different
candidates. It clearly increases the
chance of both accidental misvotes and
freak outcomes.
>> Stewart Drummond Hood campaigned as the
football club's mascot of a monkey, was
duly elected mayor of Hartlepool.
>> [applause]
>> Today, Mr. Drummond, with a budget of
105 million, was being pursued by a
journalist dressed up as a gorilla as he
tried to get serious.
>> In the UK, the equivalent hurdles are so
low as to be almost non-existent. You
still need to fill out nomination
papers, but those papers only ask for 10
signatures. You only need to live in the
constituency that you're planning
[music] to run in, but this just isn't a
particularly big threshold to pass. John
Harvey has admitted that, in order to
run as Lord Buckethead in 2017, he
managed to collect all of his required
signatures by simply traveling to
Maidenhead and asking some people in a
Costa Coffee to do him a favor. Slightly
more notable is the deposit. If you want
to run as a member of Parliament in the
UK, you not only need to complete your
nomination papers, but also pay a
deposit of 500 pounds. [music]
You hand this over to someone at your
local council, who is responsible for
running the election, who will then hold
on to your 500 quid until election day.
If you manage to get more than 5% of the
vote, the council will give you your 500
pounds back. If you get less than that,
however, you lose it. This is supposed
to act in the same way as ballot access
requirements in other countries. The
premise is that it dissuades anyone from
running who doesn't at least think that
they might have a chance of winning,
because everyone, in theory, wants to
get their deposit back. The problem is
that 500 quid just isn't that much
money. For anyone watching who isn't a
regular user of Great British pounds,
that's slightly less than a PS5 or about
two Roomba's. If you get two, they can
fight. I should find a video of uh
someone with two Roomba's nearby knives
on the top. Like, maybe we just play
that.
>> If it seems like your idea of fun is
cheaper to spend a few weeks wandering
around Makerfield or Clacton or wherever
else wearing a funny hat than it is to
spend a week in Tenerife. But, it wasn't
exactly meant to be this way. Deposits
were first introduced into the British
electoral system with the passing of the
Representation of the People Act 1918.
And they were thought up precisely to
defend British democracy against what
George Cave, the Home Secretary at the
time, called "mere freak candidates" and
to ensure that voters were only
presented with what another politician
called "genuine substantial men" to vote
for. The reason this hadn't been
necessary before was that prior to 1918,
candidates had been expected to cover
the whole cost of holding the election
themselves. Once election day came, the
local returning officer would hand you
and your fellow candidates with a bill
for all of the ballot papers and little
pencils [music] and signage and such. If
you found yourself running against just
one opponent, you could end up with a
pretty hefty bill to pay equivalent to
tens of thousands of pounds in today's
money. That's like a whole army of
Roomba's. The Representation of the
People Act 1918 saw the state absorb the
cost of running elections instead. And
the deposit was partly a way of ensuring
that these costs weren't unnecessarily
inflated by no-hopers.
But, it was also driven by a certain
fear of the electorate. The 1918 Act was
a huge moment in the democratization of
Britain. It saw the size of the
electorate triple as the vote was
extended to all men over the age of 21
and women over the age of 30 who met
certain property qualifications.
Adding in a deposit ensured that these
new working class voters would at least
only be able to choose between people of
wealthy enough means to stand. See, when
it was first introduced, the UK's
election deposit was set at £150.
That's equivalent to £7,581.71
[music]
p today's money, or for international
viewers, about the price of a fairly
reliable, if not particularly fancy,
second-hand car. For an ordinary working
person in the 1910s, however, that was
somewhere between 6 months and a year's
worth of salary. No one was going to
risk 6 months worth of salary just for
an opportunity to stand on the stage of
their local leisure center wearing an
Elmo costume. It was even more
foreboding when you took into account
that getting your deposit back required
you to win a full 12.5%
of the vote. Fascinatingly though, the
Representation of the People Act didn't
include any provisions for increasing
the level of the deposit in line with
inflation, which meant that over time
that massive deposit of 150 quid began
to plummet in value.
By the time Screaming Lord Sutch first
ran in Stratford-upon-Avon in 1963, the
inflation-adjusted cost of entering an
election had fallen by 2/3 to just 2,818
pounds in today's money. That's about
the cost of a MacBook Pro 14-inch with a
nanotexture display and an M5 Pro chip
and 18 cores of CPU, but no upgrades to
the memory or storage and also no power
adapter. Not getting a power adapter is
an option now,
which I think is good for the
environment. When the Official Monster
Raving Loony Party was launched in
Ashburton in 1982, it fell in again to
be worth just 550 pounds and [music] 22
p in today's money, which is still a PS5
or two Roombas. Although they didn't
have Roombas in 1985. R- RIP Maggie
Thatcher, you would have loved the
Roomba.
Um
Would she have?
>> The sort of scabs.
>> The result was that the early 1980s saw
an explosion of novelty candidates, not
unlike that which we're seeing today. In
1985 then, the UK government under
Margaret Thatcher passed another
representation of the people act.
Presumably she hadn't been impressed by
having to stand alongside Screaming
[music] Lord Sutch while waiting for her
election results. Among other things,
the act increased the size of the
deposit required to run to become a
member of parliament to £500 in 1985
money, or about £1,600
in today's money.
That's just less than the price of a
Herman Miller Aeron desk chair. Making
this video really made me miss the Argos
catalog cuz I think that would have been
really useful for a piece of comparison.
After some popular backlash however, a
compromise was reached which reduced the
percentage of the vote that you had to
achieve to get your deposit back from
12.5% to just 5%. If this helps repair
the barrier to entry for UK elections,
what's baffling is that no one thought
to add in a clause about inflation the
second time round. And in the time
since, no government has dared to
consider it. Naturally then, the value
of the deposit has fallen again and
again in the 41 years since it was last
revised. In 1985, running for election
would have cost you the equivalent of
1,630
pints of beer. In 2026, it's probably
only around 100 pints, at which point it
begins to seem a lot more attractive.
We've ended up with this beautifully
bizarre system in which the bar for
running for office is outstandingly low.
And through a weird sequence of events,
it's meant that novelty candidates
[music]
might actually be about to matter.
>> The last 2 years I've really enjoyed the
job of being an MP. The people, the
constituency, it's an office that I
genuinely, genuinely adore.
>> In April of 2026, The Guardian published
an article revealing that the MP for
Clacton [music] and leader of the Reform
Party, Nigel Farage, had accepted a
donation of £5 million
from a cryptocurrency billionaire with
Christopher Harborne. That's enough to
get you a fairly reliable second-hand
The donation had come at a crucial point
in Farage's career. The 2024 general
election was getting near, and Farage
had said that he wasn't going to stand.
Soon after accepting the cash, however,
he seemed to change his mind.
>> Happy birthday, huge fan.
>> As is often the case, it wasn't so much
the crime which tripped Farage up as the
cover-up. See, on being elected, British
MPs are required to register any
donations or gifts that they've received
in the year prior to taking office in
what's called the Members' Register of
Interests. This is to ensure that there
is transparency with where politicians
are getting their money from. Farage,
however, decided that he didn't need to
declare his donation. His attempt at an
explanation was that he didn't need to
register the donation as it wasn't a
political donation, but simply a
personal gift of £5 million quid from
one friend to another. We won't be
there. He would then claim that the
money was for security.
Even if these explanations had managed
to quell the criticism he was facing,
however, it didn't much matter. It soon
turned out that the £5 million
wasn't a one-off. It was soon discovered
by reporters at the Sunday Times that
Nigel Farage had been accepting a range
of campaigning support from wealthy
Reform supporter called George Cottrell,
or Posh George to his friends. To make
matters worse, Cottrell, who apparently
refers to Farage as Daddy, was a
convicted fraudster, having spent 8
months in prison in the US for agreeing
to launder cash for drug traffickers who
turned out to be undercover FBI agents.
For good measure, he's also the author
of a book called How to Launder Money.
>> Is it a mistake not to declare the gifts
from George Cottrell, sir.
>> You tell your bosses you harass my
family anymore and I'll take you to
serious consequences. That's what your
organization has done this morning. Go
away.
>> Soon, Nigel Farage was being
investigated by the Parliamentary
Commissioner for Standards. The person
whose job it is to investigate
accusations of improper donations and
other conduct issues within Parliament.
For the first time in a very, very, very
long time, things were not looking good
for our Nigel. Until recently, it had
seemed that all he had to do to become
Prime Minister at the next election was
wait. But, being found guilty of
breaking the MP's code of conduct by
failing to declare these donations could
have seen him thrown out of Parliament
altogether. And so, he announced his
resignation. Or, he kind of did. On the
7th of July, 2026, Nigel Farage jumped
on a live broadcast to announce that he
would be resigning as Member of
Parliament for Clacton.
He would, however, also be standing in
the by-election which would follow in
order to try to become his own
replacement. It was a pretty brazen
attempt to pull attention away from the
scandal surrounding his financial
dealings and, instead, demonstrate that
the people who voted for him in his
constituency of Clacton simply don't
care about where his cash comes from.
>> I thought about it hard and I've decided
today, today I will resign as a Member
of Parliament for Clacton-on-Sea,
thereby forcing a by-election, which
would happen, I hope, in short order.
>> [sighs]
>> No, I've decided that the people of
Clacton
should be the judges of my actions.
>> They almost certainly don't. For what
it's worth, Clacton, the town that
Farage represents in Parliament, is just
super right wing. At the 2024 election,
Farage managed to bag 46.2%
of the vote. Made only more startling by
the fact that his closest competitor was
the Conservative Party candidate who
received 27.9%.
Just shy of three quarters of people in
this town voted either for the
Conservative Party or Reform.
>> I therefore do hereby declare that Nigel
Paul Farage is duly elected as the
Member of Parliament for the Clacton
constituency.
>> All of this presented the UK's other
major political parties with a
predicament. Farage was almost certainly
going to win this self-imposed
by-election, regardless of how much
money they threw at it. They knew that
he would take every opportunity to
present the contest as a noble David and
Goliath-esque struggle between him and
the establishment. You know, if David
had been armed with a sling and also 5
million pounds he'd been given by a
crypto dude. So, they did something
unexpected. One by one, the UK's major
political parties announced that they
would refuse to participate in Farage's
circus. He would be denied his big
confrontation,
except maybe against one guy. Well,
actually a few. Amid 12 minutes after
Nigel Farage announced his resignation,
Count Binface took to X to declare that
he would be running. And as the
Conservatives, Labour, the Lib Dems, the
Greens, and others all began to pull
out, he quickly became the only
household name likely to be in the race.
Very soon, the country was facing a
reality in which Count Binface had
become the only person who might
possibly, maybe be able to foil Nigel
Farage's plans.
>> These are serious times.
>> But right
>> Why don't you bin off the bin on
Newsnight now? We know that your name is
John, and we know really a lot about
you. Isn't this time for serious times
to bin off the bin?
>> Oh, here we go. I mean, has anyone here
seen Return of the Jedi? Nobody wants to
know what's underneath a recycler. It's
disgusting.
>> So, could the bin win? Almost certainly
not. Sorry. Although, it's probably
worth saying he probably does have more
of a chance of winning than any
candidate from a more legitimate party
might. Again, Clacton is just super
right-wing. Nigel Farage's level of
support within the constituency is so
large that beating him basically
requires getting everyone else in the
town to vote for one single other
candidate. In recent by-elections
elsewhere in the country, tactical
voting to defeat Reform has worked. In
Wakefield, voters piled in behind
Labour's Andy Burnham. Whilst in Gorton
and Denton, they lined up behind the
Green Party's Hannah Spencer. Both
candidates were supported by a lot of
tactical voters as well as their own
party's natural supporters. But, Clacton
is so right-wing that beating Farage
would likely involve having to convince
every single Labour, Lib Dem, and Green
Party voter to back the Conservative
candidate. Which just [music] isn't
going to happen. Count Binface, by
contrast, comes without the same
baggage. That the most serious of his
campaign pledges amounts to abolishing
all auto-renew subscriptions means that
there's very little to stop anyone who
doesn't like Nigel Farage from backing
him. He might even be able to peel off a
few Reform voters in a way that the
Labour Party or the Greens would
probably never been able to. What it
does mean is that Nigel Farage has
already kind of lost. Yes, he might win
his seat back, but in order to do so,
he'll have to stand on stage alongside
Count Binface, three separate members of
the official Monster Raving Loony Party,
and someone called Woke Trump. There are
also a bunch of other bargain basement
fascists alongside a candidate from the
Everyone Is God Party, which describes
itself as the only political party in
the world that uncompromisingly follows
all moral values. This mad clips.
A mad mad party.
>> Politics is not driven by politics.
It's driven by humans and the decisions
we make.
And humans are driven by psychology.
And psychology at the root is sex.
>> It really is going to be a collection of
loonies and loonies. Oh, and also a
bunch of like anti-vaxers and real white
supremacists. Well, this particular
election is likely to be a lot of fun.
This time around, however, there's every
chance it could be the twilight of
novelty candidates. I would be surprised
if very soon there weren't high-profile
calls to increase deposits or add some
other form of ballot access requirements
to avoid elections involving 30-odd
candidates. And I do mean 30-odd
candidates becoming the norm.
>> And yet, novelty candidates have also
become a much-loved part of the British
electoral process.
>> Even if it wasn't intentional, they
become representative of a democratic
system in which anyone could win. And in
which, with the country on the threshold
of possibly electing its most far-right
government ever, anyone can find
themselves as the last redoubt against
fascism.
Even a bin. One of the biggest benefits
of Count Bin Face being an intergalactic
space warrior rather than a bog-standard
citizen in the UK is that not being in
the UK, he isn't usually subject to the
various rules which are being rolled out
with regard to the blocking of certain
websites or age gating [music] of the
internet. Laws like the Online Safety
Act and the upcoming ban on under-16s
using social media require users in the
UK to hand over photos of their ID or
other personal information to unheard of
third-party companies to be able to
access much of the [music] web.
Fortunately, today's video sponsor,
Proton VPN, allows you to take a
different approach. You might have heard
of Proton before. Their popular Proton
Mail email product is used by
journalists, activists, and others whom
privacy is of vital importance. And
Proton VPN allows you to have that same
privacy throughout all of your internet
browsing. Proton VPN allows you to
[music] choose where in the world you'd
like the internet to think that you are.
One benefit is that this allows you to
see the localized versions of different
websites or streaming services. Proton
VPN, for example, can get you access to
the BBC iPlayer even whilst you're
outside of the country, or get you
access to the US version of Netflix.
But, if you're in the UK and you tell it
that you're in the US or somewhere else,
you also won't have to send off a
picture of your passport to some shady
third-party servers. And because Proton
is controlled by a foundation and based
in the privacy-obsessed Switzerland, you
can rely on them to always put your
privacy and transparency [music]
first. Proton VPN is even open source,
so their code is also publicly available
for anyone to inspect at any point to
ensure they're not up to any funny
business in the background there. Better
still, if you sign up using the link on
screen now or by clicking the link down
below, you can get 64% off a Proton VPN
subscription to protect your privacy
today. Thanks so much to Proton VPN for
sponsoring today's video.
All that's left me to do is to say a
massive thank you to the people who
support my work over on the top tier of
my Patreon. Those people are Richard,
Gary, Dick on Spain, Bill Mitchell, ZC
Reese, Zoe Alden, Alexander Blank, Niels
de Bildt Gaard, Sophia R, Sergio Suarez,
Richard Rapun, Gabriel Coke, Jimmy Dunn,
Fiasco Linguini, The Third Workshop,
Emil Jaraba, Yilmazan, Paulius Eidakus,
and Sam Fortunato. If you want to join
them and get early access to videos, uh
little insights into what we're working
on, and a bunch of other stuff. You can
find out how to do so at
patreon.com/tomnicholas.
Thank you so much for watching once
again, and I'll see you in the next
video.